Guide to the John Kissam papers 1974.133
Brooklyn Historical Society
John Kissam papers
1778-1823, 1864-1868
Brooklyn Historical Society
Kissam, John
1974.133
0.1 Linear Feet in 15 folders and one flat file folder.
The John Kissam papers principally include correspondence and orders to Major Kissam, a Loyalist, concerning the Queens County Militia during the British occupation of New York and Long Island during the American Revolution.
Box A0012
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eleanor Wiggins, April 8, 1959.
Arrangement
Documents concerning John Kissam, which are the bulk of the collection, are presented first, followed by the Wiggins certificates and the Confederate muster roll.
Biographical note
John Kissam (1748-1828) was a farmer in Flower Hill, a village in Queens County (N.Y.) at the time, but which became part of North Hempstead, Nassau County in the twentieth century. During the American Revolution, Kissam was a Loyalist and was given the rank of major in the Queens County Militia on December 9, 1776, during the British occupation of New York and Long Island. On June 30, 1781, he was kidnapped from his home by revolutionaries and taken to Connecticut. He was paroled and then exchanged for another prisoner in October 1781. Back on Long Island, he continued in the militia. Among other services, he oversaw the delivery of wood from Long Islanders at the order of the British authorities. At the close of the war, Kissam left for Nova Scotia, but returned to Long Island by 1786. He was Clerk of the Board of Supervisors of Queens County from 1797 to 1820. He also served as a vestryman in St. George's Episcopal Church in Hempstead and a warden at Christ Church in Manhasset.
Sources
Onderdonk, Henry Jr. Documents and letters intended to illustrate the revolutionary incidents of Queens County, N.Y. F127.Q3.Q4 v.4, pp. 31-59.
Kissam, Edward. The Kissam family in America from 1644 to 1826. CS71.C3883, p. 25.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
The Archibald Hamilton and Oliver De Lancey Revolutionary War order book (1974.049) includes orders issued by these two commanders.
The Landon family papers (1977.025) include documents concerning Col. Archibald Hamilton and the Queens County Militia.
The Henry Onderdonk papers (ARC.045) include transcriptions of Kissam correspondence. Onderdonk published at least some of the documents in the collection in his Documents and letters intended to illustrate the revolutionary incidents of Queens County, N.Y. (call number F127.Q3.Q4 v.4); see pages 31-59.
Scope and Contents
The John Kissam papers principally include correspondence and orders, dating from 1778-1781, to Major Kissam concerning the Queens County (N.Y.) Militia during the American Revolution. The subjects relate mostly to the taking of property, especially wood-cutting; authorization for movements about Long Island and to New York; and meeting troop musters. There are a small number of post-war items concerning Kissam including a receipt book (1787-1806), a statement by a Mr. Hart (likely rector Seth Hart of Christ Church, Hempstead) regarding his financial difficulties (undated), and a referral to Kissam of a candidate for the church at North Hempstead (1823).
The collection also includes election (1865) and discharge (1868) certificates for Corporal Platt (or Pratt) Wiggins from the New York State National Guard. The collection includes the August 1864 muster roll of Company K of the 12th Georgia Infantry Regiment, Confederate States of America.
Separated Materials
Various objects received with the collection were separated from the documents in 1968. These objects included: one rolling pin; one pair of slippers and one beaded bag belonging to Elizabeth Kissam Underhill (1816); penknife; drawings; children's books; dispatch bag from Kamchatka; a nineteenth century fan with ivory handle; and a judge's ribbon from the Queens County Agricultural Society.
Certificates; Receipts (financial records); Queens County (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783; Muster rolls; Military occupation damages |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Orders (military records); Correspondence; Queens County (N.Y.); Hamilton, Archibald; Confederate States of America. Army. Georgia Infantry Regiment, 12th; Kissam, John; Wiggins family; Queens County (N.Y.). Militia
- Colonel Archibald Hamilton papers, 1778-1781 (Box A0012, Folder 1)
- Ludlow, G.G., 1778 (Box A0012, Folder 2)
- Ludlow, George D., 1781 (Box A0012, Folder 3)
- Smith, Major General, 1780 (Box A0012, Folder 4)
- Livingston, Philip J., 1780 (Box A0012, Folder 5)
- Poers, John P., 1781 (Box A0012, Folder 6)
- Crosbie, William, 1781 (Box A0012, Folder 7)
- deWurmb, Lt. Colonel, 1781, 1783 (Box A0012, Folder 8)
- Miles, Col. D., 1781 (Box A0012, Folder 9)
- Wood deliveries, undated (Box A0012, Folder 10)
- Receipt book, 1787-1806 (Box A0012, Folder 11)
- Reverand Hart bankruptcy plea, undated (Box A0012, Folder 12)
- Moore, John H., 1823 (Box A0012, Folder 13)
- Army warrant to Pratt Wiggins, 1865 (Box A0012, Folder 14)
- Discharge of Platt Wiggins, 1868 (Box A0012, Folder 15)
- Confederate muster roll, 1864 (Folder Flat File)